A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Business, Series 1 FA141
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Business, Series 1
1929-1979
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Seitz, Frederick
FA141
5.79 Cubic Feet 15 document boxes
Biographical/Historical note
Frederick Seitz (b. July 4, 1911, d. March 2, 2008) was a physicist and science administrator. He has made fundamental contributions to the theory of solids, nuclear physics, fluorescence, and crystals, and has been a leader in the post - World War II scientific establishment in the United States. From 1968-1978 Seitz was president of the Rockefeller University.
Seitz entered Stanford University in January 1929, where he started out as a biochemistry major, but soon focused on mathematics and physics. He graduated from Stanford in three years with a degree in mathematics, and started doctoral studies in physics at Princeton University at the beginning of 1932. Completing his doctorate in 1934 Seitz remained at Princeton as a Proctor Fellow, and in 1935 was appointed as an instructor at the University of Rochester. In 1939 Seitz moved to the University of Pennsylvania first as assistant professor, 1939-1941, and then associate professor, 1941-1942, in the Morgan Laboratory of Physics. Seitz moved to the University of Illinois in 1949 to accept an appointment as a professor of Physics. In the 40s and 50s Seitz's research focused on the properties of crystals. His published works included studies of dislocations and imperfections in crystal structures, the effect of irradiation on crystals, and the process of diffusion in crystalline materials. In 1962 Seitz was elected president of the National Academy of Sciences in Washington, a position which he held for 6 years. In that same year, he became a trustee of the Rockefeller University and in 1968 he went on to become president of the Rockefeller University. In 1973 he received the National Medal of Science, the nation's highest award in science, for his contributions "to the foundation of the modern quantum theory of the solid state of matter."
Among his numerous honors and awards, Dr. Seitz received the Franklin Medal in 1965, the Herbert Hoover Medal in 1968, the Defense Department Distinguished Service Award in Awards in 1968, the NASA distinguished Service in 1969, the Compton Award, the highest award of the American Institute of Physics, in 1970, and the James Madison Medal of Princeton University in 1978. In 1979 he received his second NASA Distinguished Public Service Medal presented for his "dedicated service as chairman of the NASA Space Program Advisory Council from 1973 to 1977. " In addition to the Rockefeller University, 26 universities in this country and abroad have awarded him honorary degrees. In 1983 he received the Fourth Vannevar Bush Award presented by the National Science Board of the National Science Foundation and the R. Loveland Memorial Award of the American College of Physicians. From 1978 to 1983 he served as vice chairman of the Board of Trustees of the Memorial Sloan - Kettering Cancer Center.
Other memberships include the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, The Century Club, the Bohemian Club, the American Philosophical Society, the American Society for Metals, the American Institute of Mining, Metallurgy and Petroleum Engineers, the American Crystallographic Society, the Optical Society of America, the Washington Academy of Science, and a number of European scientific academies.
Arrangement note
As received.
File Plan note
Former Classification: 1 304-2
Other Finding Aids
FA815 Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Chronological Files, Series 2. FA816 Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Archive Center, Series 3. FA817 Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Campus, Series 4. FA818 Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, General Administration, Series 5. FA819 Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Personal, Biographical and Miscellaneous, Series 6.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: annual reports, financial reports, and budget material.
Physical sciences; Physics; Operations management; New York (N.Y.); Regional planning -- New York (N.Y.); Urban policy -- New York (State) -- New York; Biology -- Research
- Business, 1929-1979; 1; 6.6 Cubic Feet 15 document boxes.
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes Annual Reports, Financial Reports and Statements of Receipts.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1929 October 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1930 October 31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1931 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1932 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1933 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1934 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1936 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1937 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1938 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1939 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1940 October 25 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1941 October 31 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1942 October 30 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1943 October 29 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1944 October 27 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1945 October 26 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1946 October 25 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1947 October 31 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1948 October 29 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1949 October 28 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1950 October 27 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1951 October 26 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1952 October 31 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1953 October 30 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1954 October 15 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1955 October 26 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Annual Report of the Business Manager, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report of the Director of the Budget and Special Services, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report of the Director of the Budget and Special Services, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report of the Director of the Budget and Special Services (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Financial Report, 1962 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Financial Report, 1963 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Financial Report, 1964 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Financial Report, 1965 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Financial Report, 1966 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Financial Report, 1967 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Financial Report, 1968 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Financial Report Supplement, 1968 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Faculty and Students Club, Inc. - Annual Report, 1968 July 1-1969 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Financial Report, 1969 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Financial Report Supplement, 1969 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Financial Report, 1972 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Financial Report Supplement, 1972 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Rockefeller University Budget for, 1969 July 1-1970 June 30 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Rockefeller University Budget for, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Appraisal Report, 1972 January 31 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Proposed Indirect Cost Rate for the Year 1969-1970, Final, 1971 August 2 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Financial Report Supplement, 1970 June 30 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Financial Report Supplement, 1971 June 30 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Statement of Receipts and Disbursements, 1968 July 1-October 31 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Budget Trends, 1959-1960 1964-1965 1965-1966 1966-1967 1967-1968 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Statement of Receipts and Disbursements, 1968 July 1-1969 January 31 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Statement of Receipts and Disbursements, 1969 July 1-October 31 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Statement of Receipts and Disbursements, 1969 July 1-November 30 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Statement of Receipts and Disbursements, 1969 July 1-December 31 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Statement of Receipts and Disbursements, 1969 July 1-1970 January 31 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Statement of Receipts and Disbursements, 1969 July 1-1970 February 28 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Statement of Receipts and Disbursements, 1969 July 1-1970 March 31 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Statement of Receipts and Disbursements, 1969 July 1-1970 April 30 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Statement of Receipts and Disbursements, 1969 July 1-1970 May 31 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Statement of Receipts and Disbursements, 1969 July 1-1970 June 30 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Board of Trustees Meeting, 1971 January 16 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Board of Trustees Meeting, 1972 January 18 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Board of Trustees Meeting, 1972 May 17 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Board of Trustees Meeting, 1972 October 31 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Board of Trustees Meeting, 1973 January 16 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Board of Trustees Meeting, 1973 May 3 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Board of Trustees Meeting, 1974 October 8 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Board of Trustees Meeting, 1975 January 14 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Board of Trustees Meeting, 1975 May 23 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Board of Trustees Meeting, 1975 October 23 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Board of Trustees Meeting, 1976 January 30 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Board of Trustees Meeting, 1976 May 28 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Meeting of the Executive Committee Board of Trustees, 1972 March 16 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Meeting of the Executive Committee Board of Trustees, 1972 July 11 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Meeting of the Executive Committee Board of Trustees, 1972 October 4 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Meeting of the Executive Committee Board of Trustees, 1973 January 8 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Meeting of the Executive Committee Board of Trustees, 1973 August 1 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Meeting of the Executive Committee Board of Trustees, 1973 October 30 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Meeting of the Executive Committee Board of Trustees, 1974 January 15 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Meeting of the Executive Committee Board of Trustees, 1974 April 2 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Meeting of the Executive Committee Board of Trustees, 1975 February 11 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Meeting of the Executive Committee Board of Trustees, 1975 May 5 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Meeting of the Executive Committee Board of Trustees, 1975 July 22 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Meeting of the Executive Committee Board of Trustees, 1975 October 23 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Meeting of the Executive Committee Board of Trustees, 1976 January 29 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Meeting of the Executive Committee Board of Trustees, 1976 March 9 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the Meeting of the Executive Committee Board of Trustees, 1976 May 27 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Financial Reports, 1972 July-1973 June (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Financial Reports, 1972 August-1973 July (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Financial Reports, 1973 August-1974 July (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Financial Reports, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Financial Reports, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Financial Reports, 1974 July-1975 June (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Financial Reports, 1975 July-1976 June (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Financial Reports, 1975 July-1976 June (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Financial Reports, 1975-1976 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Accounting System, 1970 April 10 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Advance Plan, 1962-1973 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Children's College Awards Program, 1966-1975 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Controller: Functions and Responsibilities, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Committee on Tuition Assistance, 1964-1967 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Faculty Salaries, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Cost Effectiveness Suggestions, 1971-1973 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Committee on Faculty Benefits, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Indirect Costs, Overhead, 1962-1969 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Statements of Receipts and Expenditures, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - FY, 1968 July-1969 June (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Financial Reports, FY, 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Indirect Costs, Budget and Finance, 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Materials for Auditors, re: FY, 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - FY, 1969 July-1970 June (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - FY 1970: Budget and Finance Papers presented to the meeting of the Board of Trustees, 1970 May 11 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Financial Report, 1970 June 30 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Financial Report Supplement, 1970 June 30 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - FY 1971: Budget and Finance papers presented at the meeting of the Board of Trustees, 1970 October 20 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Commission on Independent Colleges and Universities: Studies of the cost of fields and levels of degree programs, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Dental Insurance papers, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Unemployment Insurance, 1969-1971 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Budget and Finance: Personnel - General, 1969-1971 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Travel Insurance, 1969-1971 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the meeting of the Board of Trustees, 1971 January 28 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Financial Papers as presented at the meeting of the Board of Trustees, 1971 May 4 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, Financial Matters, 1969-1972 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Hospitals Joint Project, Wages and Salaries, 1970-1971 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Financial Reports, FY, 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - FY, 1970 July-1971 June (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Grant Procedures: Memorandum dated, 1971 February 15 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Blue Cross/Blue Shield, 1970-1972 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - FY, 1971 July-1972 June (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Financial Reports, FY, 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Pay Board Report, 1971-1972 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - RU Staff Abroad, Cost of Living, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Campus Planning: Clarke & Rapuano, Inc., RU Master Plan, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Budget and Finance, Personnel - Individual, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Overhead Formula, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Accounting Systems Notebook, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Group Life, Long Term or Total Disability Insurance, 1969-1974 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Tax Abatement/Exemption, General, 1970-1974 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Campus Planning: Clarke and Rapuano, Inc., Correspondence, 1972-1974 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Financial Report, 1974 June 30 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - FY 1974 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - FY 1974 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Major Medical Insurance, 1969-1975 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Insurance, General, 1970-1975 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Financial Report, 1975 June 30 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Expenditures - Total RU through, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - FY 1975, Working Papers (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - FY 1975, Financial Statements (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - FY 1975, Revenues and Expenditures (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Expenditures - Total RU, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Budget and Finance, General, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Grants: General, 1962-1976 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Budgetary Stringencies, Personnel Freeze, 1970-1976 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Accounting - General, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - FY 1976, Working Papers (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - FY 1976, Financial Statements (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - FY 1976, re: Budget Requests (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - FY 1976, projected budget and comparison with FY, 1975 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - FY 1976, Budget Revisions (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - FY 1976, Preliminary Budget (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - FY 1977 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - FY, Financial Statements, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - FY, Budget Requests, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - FY, Capital Budget, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - FY 1978 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - FY 1979 (Box 15, Folder 7)